{
  "title": "Engineering_Mathematics - Engineering_Mathematics — Slot 10 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Engineering_Mathematics — Slot 10",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>\\(\\lim_{x\\rightarrow \\infty }\\frac{x-sin x}{x+cos x}\\) equals <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2008)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>-1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\infty\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(-\\infty\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399/gate2008-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Eigen vectors of \\(\\begin{bmatrix} 1 &amp;&amp; \\cos \\theta \\\\ \\cos \\theta &amp;&amp; 1 \\end{bmatrix}\\) are <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} a^n &amp;&amp; 1 \\\\ 0 &amp;&amp; a^n \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} a^n &amp;&amp; n \\\\ 0 &amp;&amp; a^n \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} a^n &amp;&amp; na^{n-1} \\\\ 0 &amp;&amp; a^n \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} a^n &amp;&amp; na^{n-1} \\\\ -n &amp;&amp; a^n \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} a^n &amp;&amp; na^{n-1} \\\\ -n &amp;&amp; a^n \\end{bmatrix}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/49479/isro2007-09\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(P_1, P_2,\\dots , P_n\\) be n points in the xy-plane such that no three of them are collinear. For every pair of points \\(P_i\\) and \\(P_j\\), let \\(L_{ij}\\) be the line passing through them. Let \\(L_{ab}\\) be the line with the steepest gradient among all \\(n(n -1)/2\\) lines.<br>\nThe time complexity of the best algorithm for finding \\(P_a\\) and \\(P_b\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta\\left(n\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta\\left(n\\log n\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta\\left(n\\log^2 n\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta\\left(n^2\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta\\left(n\\log n\\right)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3533/gate2007-it-81\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(P_1, P_2,\\dots , P_n\\) be n points in the xy-plane such that no three of them are collinear. For every pair of points \\(P_i\\) and \\(P_j\\), let \\(L_{ij}\\) be the line passing through them. Let \\(L_{ab}\\) be the line with the steepest gradient among all \\(n(n -1)/2\\) lines.<br>Which one of the following properties should necessarily be satisfied ? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(P_{a}\\) and \\(P_{b}\\) are adjacent to each other with respect to their x-coordinate</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Either \\(P_{a}\\) or \\(P_{b}\\) has the largest or the smallest y-coordinate among all the points</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The difference between x-coordinates \\(P_{a}\\) and \\(P_{b}\\) is minimum</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(P_{a}\\) and \\(P_{b}\\) are adjacent to each other with respect to their x-coordinate</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3532/gate2007-it-80\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>The trapezoidal method is used to evaluate the numerical value of \\(\\int_{0}^{1}e^x dx\\).  Consider the following values for the step size h.<br>\ni.   \\(10^{-2}\\)<br>\nii.  \\(10^{-3}\\)<br>\niii. \\(10^{-4}\\)<br>\niv.  \\(10^{-5}\\)<br>\nFor which of these values of the step size h, is the computed value guaranteed to be correct to seven decimal places. Assume that there are no round-off errors in the computation. <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>iv only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>iii and iv only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>ii, iii and iv only</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>i, ii, iii and iv</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>iii and iv only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3455/gate2007-it-22\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Let A be the matrix \\(\\begin{bmatrix}3 &amp;1 \\\\ 1&amp;2\\end{bmatrix}\\). What is the maximum value of \\(x^TAx\\) where the maximum is taken over all x that are the unit eigenvectors of A? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{(5 + \\sqrt{5})}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{(5 - \\sqrt{5})}{2}\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{(5 + \\sqrt{5})}{2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3433/gate2007-it-2\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Consider the series \\(x_{n+1}=\\frac{x_{n}}{2}+\\frac{9}{8x_{n}},x_{0}=0.5\\) obtained from the Newton-Raphson method. The series converges to <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1.5</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\sqrt{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1.6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1.4</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>1.5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1226/gate2007-28#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Consider the set of (column) vectors defined by <br> \\(X=\\{x\\in R^{3}|x_{1}+x_{2}+x_{3}=0, \\; where \\; x^{T}=[x_{1},x_{2},x_{3}]^{T}\\}.\\)<br> Which of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\{[1,-1,0]^{T},[1,0,-1]^{T}\\}\\) is a basis for the subspace X.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\{[1,-1,0]^{T},[1,0,-1]^{T}\\}\\) is a linearly independent set, but it does not span X and therefore is not a basis of X.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>X is not a subspace of \\(R^{3}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\{[1,-1,0]^{T},[1,0,-1]^{T}\\}\\) is a basis for the subspace X.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1225/gate2007-27#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Let A be a 4 x 4 matrix with eigenvalues -5, -2, 1, 4. Which of the following is an\neigenvalue of <br>\\(\\begin{bmatrix} A &amp; I\\\\ I&amp;A \\end{bmatrix}\\)<br>  where I is the 4 x 4 identity matrix? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>-5</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>-7</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1223/gate2007-25#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following two statements about the function f(x)=|x|:<br><br>\nP.  f(x) is continuous for all real values of x <br>\nQ. f(x) is differentiable for all real values of x <br><br>\nWhich of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>P is true and Q is false.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>P is false and Q is true.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Both P and Q are true.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Both P and Q are false.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>P is true and Q is false.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1200/gate2007-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>x+y/2=9 <br>\n3x+y=10<br>\nWhat can be said about the Gauss-Siedel iterative method for solving the above set of linear equations? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>it will converge</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>It will diverse</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>It will neither converge nor diverse</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>It is not applicable</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>it will converge</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3621/gate2006-it-77\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>x+y/2=9 <br>\n3x+y=10<br>\nThe value of the Frobenius norm for the above system of equations is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0.5</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0.75</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1.5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3620/gate2006-it-76\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>The following definite integral evaluates to <br>\\(\\int_{-\\infty}^{0} e^ {-\\left(\\frac{x^2}{20} \\right )}dx\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\pi \\sqrt{10}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\sqrt{10}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\pi\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3567/gate2006-it-28\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Match the following iterative methods for solving algebraic equations and their orders of convergence.<br>\\(\\begin{array}{|l|l|l|l|} \\hline &amp; \\text { Method } &amp; &amp; \\text { Order of Convergence } \\\\ \\hline \\text { 1. } &amp; \\text { Bisection } &amp; \\text { P. } &amp; \\text { 2 or more } \\\\ \\hline \\text { 2. } &amp; \\text { Newton-Raphson } &amp; \\text { Q. } &amp; 1.62 \\\\ \\hline \\text { 3. } &amp; \\text { Secant } &amp; \\text { R. } &amp; 1 \\\\ \\hline \\text { 4. } &amp; \\text { Regula falsi } &amp; \\text { S. } &amp; 1 \\text { bit per iteration } \\\\ \\hline \\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I-R, II-S, III-P, IV-Q</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I-S, II-R, III-Q, IV-P</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I-S, II-Q, III-R, IV-P</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>I-S, II-P, III-Q, IV-R</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>I-S, II-P, III-Q, IV-R</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3566/gate2006-it-27\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>What are the eigenvalues of the matrix P given below <br>\\(P= \\begin{pmatrix} a &amp;1 &amp;0 \\\\ 1&amp; a&amp; 1\\\\ 0&amp;1 &amp;a \\end{pmatrix}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(a, a -\\sqrt2, a + \\sqrt2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>a, a, a</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0, a, 2a</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>-a, 2a, 2a</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(a, a -\\sqrt2, a + \\sqrt2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3565/gate2006-it-26\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}